<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Congratulatory poem on the meeting together of the Parliament according to His Majesties gracious concession the 21th of this instant October</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5826</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29679</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11192329</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11192329</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46644</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34283)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46644)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1438:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Congratulatory poem on the meeting together of the Parliament according to His Majesties gracious concession the 21th of this instant October</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Langley Curtis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:46644:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46644:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->
            <head>A Congratulatory POEM ON <hi>The meeting together</hi> OF THE PARLIAMENT, According to his MAJESTIES Gracious CONCESSION The 21th of this inſtant <hi>October.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>THe Common-wealth may Repreſented be,</l>
            <l>By a brave Frigot, ſailing on the Sea;</l>
            <l>The King the Captain is, Who all Commands,</l>
            <l>Who ſometimes dains to Steer with his own Hands.</l>
            <l>Elſe picks ſome noted Perſon in his Realm,</l>
            <l>Whom he as Pilot, bids ſtand at the Helm.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:46644:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->
The Stern that turns the Vaſt Ship to and fro,</l>
            <l>Doth the Kings Wiſdom and his Council Show</l>
            <l>A<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d that alone the Vaſt Bulk in its Pride,</l>
            <l>Through dandgerous Seas &amp; breaking Wave; doth guide.</l>
            <l>The Sails, State Policies, without whoſe Aid.</l>
            <l>(Sometimes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>url'd up, and ſometimes wide diſplai'd</l>
            <l>To catch each Wind of State) the mighty Ship</l>
            <l>Could not ſo nimbly o're the Billows leap.</l>
            <l>The Waiſtcloaths, Streamers, Flags and Pendants be</l>
            <l>The Cerimonious Pride of Majeſty,</l>
            <l>Without which Grace and Glory ſhe would look,</l>
            <l>Like an huge Leaveleſs Oak that's Thunder-ſtrook.</l>
            <l>The Guns the Frigots Force, and main Defence,</l>
            <l>Are the Arms, or the Militia of the Prince;</l>
            <l>But the Sheet-Anchor beſt doth repreſent,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Safety in Diſtreſs, the Parliament.</l>
            <l>Whoſe Priviledges the great Gable-Rope,</l>
            <l>In Danger is its Holdfaſt and its Hope.</l>
            <l>Which Anchor is heav'd forth or weigh'd up ſtill,</l>
            <l>At the great Captains pleaſure and his Will;</l>
            <l>In chooſing Times and Seaſons when and where,</l>
            <l>His Wiſdom and his Skill does beſt appear,</l>
            <l>When the Seas Rage, the Waves go Mountains high</l>
            <l>The Winds blow rfom each Quarter of the Skie,</l>
            <l>The Face of Heav'n obſcured with black Clouds,</l>
            <l>And th' horrid ſtorm bellowing among the Shrouds;</l>
            <lg>
               <l>When through the Ship a fearful Cry doth ſound,</l>
               <l>Out with the Anchor elſe we all are drown'd;</l>
            </lg>
            <l>Then is the time the Captains Skill is found.</l>
            <lg>
               <l>The Danger's nigh, each Saylor ſhould ſubmit</l>
               <l>To the brave Captains Wiſdom, Skill and Wit,</l>
               <l>He to caſt Anchor beſt knows when 'tis fit.</l>
            </lg>
            <l>Each dangerous Shift he is ſuppoſed to know,</l>
            <l>Each Place where hidden Rocks or Quickſands grow.</l>
            <l>He doth the Depths of all Seas wifely ſound,</l>
            <l>Conſiders well the Nature of the Ground,</l>
            <l>Whether 't be Rocky, Sand, or Claye mold,</l>
            <l>And fit for the Sheet-Anchor to take hold;</l>
            <l>Perhaps 'tis Deep, no Bottom to be found,</l>
            <l>Or 'tis too many Fathoms to the Ground:</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46644:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->
Perhaps 'tis paved all with Rocks below,</l>
            <l>Into whoſe Sides the Anchor cannot go.</l>
            <l>Perhaps the Bottom is looſe ſhifting Sand,</l>
            <l>And then the Ship by th' Anchor is trepan'd.</l>
            <l>Whilſt it againſt the furious Tides doth ſtrive,</l>
            <l>The Anchor drags, and then the Ship doth drive.</l>
            <l>Thus by that means, by which they truſted moſt,</l>
            <l>For Safety, all's in Danger to be loſt,</l>
            <l>The Captain wiſe, not ſhook with every Fear,</l>
            <l>The Ship doth through the Raging Billows ſtear;</l>
            <l>Till he doth ſome convenient Harbour find,</l>
            <l>Safe with fit Bottom, ſhelter'd from the Wind.</l>
            <l>Where on the Waves ſhe may ſecurely Ride,</l>
            <l>And bravely with her Prow ſtem the ſtrong Tide;</l>
            <l>Then he Commands the Anchor to be caſt,</l>
            <l>Where Sails furl'd up, ſhe ſafely Rides at laſt.</l>
            <l>Our Royal Captain after many a ſtorm,</l>
            <l>Having preſerv'd the Floating Ship from harm;</l>
            <lg>
               <l>Now knowing that it may Convenient be,</l>
               <l>Bids th' Anchor to be heav'd into the Sea,</l>
               <l>To the great Joy of all the Companie.</l>
            </lg>
            <l>This is the Day, which like a New Creation,</l>
            <l>Hath been ſo greatly long'd for by the Nation.</l>
            <l>And now I hope as in a Glorious Day,</l>
            <l>Our Diſcontents will fly like Miſts away;</l>
            <l>For which all Loyal Hearts ſhould dayly pray.</l>
            <l>A brisk Gay Joy, in every Face appears,</l>
            <l>And vaniſhed is their Troubles and their Fears;</l>
            <l>The Cloudy Skie, in every Quarter Clears.</l>
            <l>The Seas which 'gainſt the Rocks, did foam and beat</l>
            <l>And to the ſhip did no ſmall danger threat;</l>
            <l>Are now grown Calm, and quietly do flow,</l>
            <l>And with a ſoft embrace ſalutes the prow.</l>
            <l>The winds are ſtill, which erſt while were ſo loud,</l>
            <l>That tore the Sails and ratl'd in the Shroud.</l>
            <l>The Sun ſhines brighr and makes a Glorious day,</l>
            <l>And wanton Dolphins round the Frigot play.</l>
            <l>Ruff <hi>Boreas</hi> who had ſtir'd up many a Wave,</l>
            <l>King <hi>Aeolus</hi> has thruſt into his Cave.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:46644:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 30 -->
And now the Frigot's Riding in the Road,</l>
            <l>Sweet <hi>Zephoras</hi> permits to go abroad.</l>
            <l>Great <hi>Neptune</hi> with his Trident ſtrook the Main,</l>
            <l>And on him ſtrait waited his numerous Train,</l>
            <l>Whom he Commanded by the Ship to ſtand,</l>
            <l>While our Great Captain did the ſame Command;</l>
            <l>The C<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck-boats Lanch'd, and all things ready be,</l>
            <l>To let the Anchor drop into the Sea</l>
            <l>May't at the Bottom find a proper Mold,</l>
            <l>And whilſt the Captain pleaſe faſt may it hold.</l>
            <l>For good ſucceſs, let all to Heaven Cry,</l>
            <l>And let each Saylor now his Buſineſs ply</l>
            <l>Let the brave Frigot be Carined now,</l>
            <l>New Dreſt, and paid ev'n from the Stem to Prow;</l>
            <l>That ſhe may in the Port long, long endure,</l>
            <l>And Ages Ride Triumphant and ſecure.</l>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Langley Curtiſs</hi> 1680.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46644:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 30 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
